<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General cyber crime | jeroenvda.eu]]></title>
  <link href="http://jeroenvda.github.io/blog/categories/general-cyber-crime/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jeroenvda.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-04T02:00:16+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jeroenvda.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeroen Vanderauwera]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why criminals want access to your machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeroenvda.github.io/2012/02/22/why-criminals-want-access-to-your-machine/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeroenvda.github.io/2012/02/22/why-criminals-want-access-to-your-machine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Numerous times I&#8217;ve heard ignorant people stating that nobody will attempt to break in to their laptop or PC, because they don&#8217;t have anything of value for a random hacker. Well, you can&#8217;t be more wrong.</p>

<p>Cyber criminals can benefit from your system in many ways. Remember that most of these guys can do stuff with your system where you didn&#8217;t even dream about.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Let me give you a few real-life examples:</p>

<ul>
<li>Install keyloggers to get passwords from all kinds of accounts.</li>
<li>Turn on the webcam and microphone to record you and manipulate the images to extort you afterwards (seems to become a trend).</li>
<li>Install ransomware, which encrypts your hard drive. The only way to get your data back is to pay the cyber criminal for the decryption key.</li>
<li>Use your system as a depot for all kinds of illegal files, including files that contain child abuse.</li>
<li>Let your system participate in an attack on different servers in a larger botnet, like a Distributed Denial of Service attack.</li>
<li>Format your hard drive</li>
<li>Steal personal data</li>
<li>&#8230;</li>
</ul>


<p>These things happen every day. The very minimum that you can do is to install AV software and a firewall and keep your virus definitions up to date. Other recommendations are to backup regularly, install an IDS, turn on extensive logging and patch where you can <img src='http://jeroenvda.eu/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_wink.gif' alt=';)' class='wp-smiley' /> .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
